{"tossups": [{"question": "According to contemporary accounts, an early ruler of this country threw two columns off of his ship and settled where they landed. Previously, it had been inhabited by Irish monks called Papar. Later, this country was absorbed by another in the Old Covenant, which was signed after a long war called the Sturlung Era and left it under Norwegian rule. The oldest parliament in the  world is this country\u2019s Althing. For 10 points, name this small volcanic country in the North Atlantic Ocean.", "answer": "<b><u>Iceland</u> </b> [Joe Nutter]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1861 John C. Fremont was criticized for putting this state under martial law. One Senator  from this state was nicknamed \u201cOld Bullion\u201d for his opposition to paper money; that was Thomas Hart Benton. Dr. John Emerson purchased Dred Scott in this state. This state\u2019s city of Independence was the start of the Oregon Trail. For the point, name this border state admitted under the Compromise of 1820.", "answer": "<b><u>Missouri</u> </b> [Bruce Arth<u>ur]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An alliance between these two countries came about after the failure to renew the  Reinsurance Treaty in 1890. The alliance between these two countries was meant to force the Triple Alliance to fight a war on two fronts. One war plan to defeat these two countries involved sweeping through Belgium and was named for von Schlieffen. For the point, name these two great powers that presented threats on either side of Imperial Germany.", "answer": "<b><u>Rus</u><u>sia</u></b>n Empire and the <b><u>France</u></b> [or Imperial <b><u>Russia</u></b> and the <b><u>French</u></b> Third Republic; or <em><b><u>Rossiy</u></b>sk<u>ay</u><b><u>a</u></b><u>Imp</u>eriya</em>and <em>La Tro<u>isieme</u></em> <em>Republique</em> <em><b><u>fr</u></b><b><u>ancaise</u></b></em>]  [P<u>atrick L</u>iao]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One empire based in this modern day nation built its capital at Lalibela and was led by the  Agaw people. A kingdom in this nation had a port at Adulis and spoke the Ge\u2019ez language, in which the <em>Kebra Negast</em> was written. Under Ezana, that kingdom in this nation converted to Christianity and its rulers were supposedly of the Solomonic Line. For the point, name this nation ruled by the Zagwe and Axumite Kingdoms, a landlocked country in the Horn of Africa.", "answer": "<b><u>Ethiopia</u> </b> [Dan Puma]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "While serving in this organization, Jon Burge tortured hundreds of African-American men. This organization arrested a British Member of Parliament while breaking up a protest that ended in the arrest of Abbie Hoffman and his six accomplices. In February 2015, this organization was  found to be operating a \u201cBlack House\u201d where suspects were held without outside contact, embarrassing Mayor Rahm Emanuel. For the point, name this law enforcement group of Illinois\u2019 largest city.", "answer": "<b><u>Chicago Police</u></b> Department [or <b><u>Chicago P.D.</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>CPD</u></b>] [Bruce Arth<u>ur]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A leader of this last name declared her intention to dissolve her country\u2019s Secretariat of Intelligence in January 2015. An arrest warrant for that politician of this last name was found in the trash of prosecutor Alberto Nisman. Another politician with this last name cleared the way for prosecution of officials who committed abuses in his country\u2019s \u201cDirty War\u201d. For the point, give this last name of the Argentine Prime Ministers Cristina and N\u00e9stor.", "answer": "<b><u>Kirchner</u></b> [accept Cristina Fern\u00e1ndez de <b><u>Kirchner</u></b>; accept N\u00e9stor <b><u>Kirchner</u></b>; accept <b><u>Fernandez</u></b> <u>before \u201cD</u>irty War\u201d]  <u>[Ryan Rose</u>nberg]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man, who served as an \u201canti-poverty czar\u201d in the Nixon administration, once  differentiated between \u201cknown knowns\u201d, \u201cknown unknowns\u201d, and \u201cunknown unknowns.\u201d This man\u2019s namesake \u201cdoctrine\u201d emphasizes high-tech weapons and air strikes rather than more ground forces, and was coined by reporters to describe his strategy during the Iraq War. For the point, name this man who also served as Secretary of Defense from 2001-2006 under George W. Bush.", "answer": "Donald Henry <b><u>Rumsfeld</u> </b> [Isaac Hirsch]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One person of this first name enlisted Jean Fernel to help her husband\u2019s sexual problems and  orchestrated the St. Bartholomew\u2019s Day Massacre as regent to Charles IX. A ruler with this first name issued the \u201cToleration of All Faiths Edict.\u201d That ruler of this name faced a revolt led by a false Peter III and presided over the second and third partitions of Poland. For the point, give this  female name common to a French queen from the Medici and a \u201cgreat\u201d empress of Russia.", "answer": "<b><u>Catherine</u></b> [or Ye<b><u>katarina</u></b>]  [Dan Puma]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The \u201cpercentages agreement\u201d was established at this meeting. The accords from this meeting called for the expansion of a government based in Lublin. Part of Sakhalin and the Kuril Islands were given to one participant in this meeting, and that participant agreed to attack the Japanese empire 90 days after Germany was defeated. For the point, name this conference between the  \u201cBig Three\u201d Allied leaders in the Crimea near the end of World War II.", "answer": "<b><u>Yalta</u></b> Conference  [Ryan Rose<u>nberg</u>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The written works that prompted this meeting include <em>Address to the Christian Nobility</em> and <em>The Babylonian Captivity of the Church.</em> This meeting occurred in response to the papal bull <em>Exsurge Domine.</em> This meeting was presided over by the Emperor Charles V, who later banned the possession of early Protestant texts. For the point, name this imperial diet of the Holy Roman Empire where Martin Luther defended his ideas from charges of heresy.", "answer": "<b><u>Diet</u> </b>of <b><u>Worms</u> </b> [Blake Neff<u>]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This war included the Battle of El Caney, where the winning side was led by Henry Lawton.  Another battle fought during this war included a heroic charge up San Juan Hill. Some have alleged that this war was encouraged by the Yellow Journalism of Joseph Pulitzer and William Randolph Hearst. One cause of this war was possibly accidental explosion of the <em>USS Maine</em> in Havana harbor. For the point, name this war which led to US control of Guam, the Philippines, and Cuba.", "answer": "<b><u>Spanish-American</u></b> War  [Evan Adam<u>s]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this city, Jerzy Kulczycki opened The Blue Bottle after recovering sacks of a certain food item from retreating Turks. A group of philosophers from this city promulgated the ideas of Ernst Mach and advocated logical positivism. The arrival of the Nazis caused the decline of the \u201ccoffee-house culture\u201d in this city, which was also where a thinker wrote <em>The Interpretation of</em> <em>Dreams</em> and <em>The Ego and the Id</em>. For the point, name this workplace of Sigmund Freud, the capital city of Austria.", "answer": "<b><u>Vienna</u></b> [or <b><u>Wien</u></b>]  [Rob Carso<u>n]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Toussaint Dubreil represented this group as a hydra being crushed beneath the feet of the king. During the War of the Three Henrys, a Dominican monk linked with this group  assassinated Henry III, ending the Valois Dynasty. During the Day of the Barricades, Henry of Guise led this group in taking over Paris. For the point, name this organization that opposed the accession of Henry of Navarre and sought to eradicate the Huguenots during the French Wars of Religion.", "answer": "<b><u>Catholic League</u></b> [accept <b><u>Holy League</u></b>]  [Blake N<u>eff]</u>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This politician initiated a controversial National Energy Program and included a  Notwithstanding Clause in the Charter of Rights and Freedoms when he repatriated his country\u2019s constitution. This predecessor of John Turner said \u201cJust Watch Me\u201d during the October Crisis and was in power during the first Quebec independence referendum. For the point, name this Liberal politician who was Prime Minister of Canada for most of the 1970s.", "answer": "Joseph Philippe Pierre Yves Elliott <b><u>Trudeau</u></b> [or <b><u>Trudeau</u></b> Sr.] [Patrick Liao]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This city was the site of a deadly 1811 theater fire that was once thought to have killed Edgar Allen Poe\u2019s parents. An 1863 bread riot occurred in this site of the first electric trolley system in the US. It was the site of Tredegar Iron Works, a major wartime manufacturing plant.  This city was the target of McClellan\u2019s Peninsula Campaign, and many of its officials fled to Danville after it fell in 1865. For the point, name this Southern city which replaced Montgomery as capital of the Confederacy.", "answer": "<b><u>Richmond</u></b>, Virginia  [Evan Adam<u>s]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In the aftermath of this event, a still on-going refugee problem studied by Benny Morris occurred which is part of the greater \u201cNakba.\u201d This event followed the heels of the passage of UN resolution 181. This event was solidified in a speech dated 5th of Iyar 5708 which noted the \u201cnatural right\u201d of a people to be \u201cmasters of their own fate,\u201d and was given by David Ben-Gurion  at an event that had the singing of \u201cHatikva.\u201d For the point, identify this 1948 event that formalized a nation that included Tel Aviv.", "answer": "The <b><u>founding</u></b> of the State of <b><u>Israel</u></b> [accept equivalents for \u201cfounding,\u201d as well as \u201c<b><u>Israeli indepen</u><u>dence</u></b>\u201d and similar answers reflecting clear knowledge]  [<u>Dan Passner]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Children in this city state were ritually whipped during a contest to steal cheese from Artemis\u2019 temple. The Eurypontid and Agiad dynasties ruled this city-state, which was partially governed by a legislative body of 30 elder men called the <em>gerousia</em>. Xerxes I won a battle over a force containing 300 hoplites from this city-state at a narrow pass in 480 BCE.For the point, name this city-state led by Leonidas at the Battle of Thermopylae.", "answer": "<b><u>Sparta</u> </b> [Chris Man<u>ners]</u>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A minor character in this series is referred to as \u201cFive\u201d because his father changed his family\u2019s names to numbers. This series\u2019 main character idolizes the baseball player Joe Shlabotnik, while another character in this series refers to another as her \u201csweet baboo.\u201d Rerun  was introduced later in this series\u2019 run, and its other characters include Sally, Schroeder, and Lucy van Pelt. For the point, name this comic strip that featured the hapless Charlie Brown, a creation of Charles Schulz.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Peanuts</u> </b></em> [Isaac Hirsc<u>h]</u>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "The McDonald Ranch House was a key assembly site for this program. A \u201cSpecial Engineer Detachment\u201d who worked on it operated IBM punch-card calculators under the supervision of Hans Bethe and Richard Feynman. Dropping pieces of paper helped Enrico Fermi calculate the yield of one of its prototypes. For the point, name this progam supervised by general Leslie Grove and directed by J. Robert Oppenheimer, which resulted in the first atomic bomb.", "answer": "The <b><u>Manhattan Project</u></b> [prompt on \u201cmaking the atomic bomb\u201d or similar answers before mention]  [Dennis Loo]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A composer from this modern country wrote the opera <em>Manru</em> and a world-famous <em>Minuet in</em> <em>G</em> before becoming its prime minister. The composer of <em>Threnody to the Victims of Hiroshima</em> is from this country. Another composer fled this country shortly before the November Uprising, which inspired his <em>Revolutionary Etude</em>. The mazurka is a folk dance from this birthplace of the composer of the <em>Minute Waltz</em>. For the point, name this European country, the home of Ignacy Paderewski, Krzysztof Penderecki, and Frederic Chopin.", "answer": "<b><u>Poland</u></b> [or the Republic of <b><u>Poland</u></b>; or Rzeczpospolita <b><u>Polska</u></b>] [Rob Carso<u>n]</u>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A foreign minister of this country, Edvard Kardelj, was the main architect of its \u201csocialist self-management\u201d policy. The Non-Aligned Movement was founded in its capital. In 1948, this communist country split ideologically from the Soviet Union. It was first led by the former partisan Josip Broz Tito, and its constituent republics included Croatia and Serbia. For the point, name this Balkan nation that broke up in 1991.", "answer": "Socialist Federal Republic of <b><u>Yugoslavia</u></b> [or Socijalisticka Federativna Republika <b><u>Jugoslavija</u></b>]  <u>[Saul Hanki</u>n]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This coach recruited the first African-American scholarship player in the ACC, Charlie Scott. He pioneered the use of per-possession statistics in college basketball and created a unique offense designed around isolation guard play. This proponent of the \u201cFour Corners\u201d offense mentored Roy Williams and coached Phil Ford and Michael Jordan. For the point, name this former coach of, and namesake of the arena now used by, the North Carolina men\u2019s basketball team.", "answer": "Dean Edwards <b><u>Smith</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Dean</u></b>]  [Ryan Rosenberg]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This kingdom was badly defeated at the Battle of Blood River by a force led by Andries Pretorius, but it crushed a force led by Lord Chelmsford at the Battle of Isandlwana. The last leader of this kingdom was captured after the fall of Ulundi, this kingdom\u2019s capital. Mpande and Cetshwayo (ketsh-WHY-oh) were rulers of this kingdom, whose military was renowned for using the assegai. For the point, name this kingdom founded by Shaka in present-day South Africa.", "answer": "<b><u>Zulu</u></b> Kingdom [or <b><u>Zulu</u></b> empire]  [Zihan Zhen<u>g]</u>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Recent cases such as <em>Vann v. Salazar</em> involve this tribe\u2019s dealings with its namesake freedmen, and this tribe formed the <em>Phoenix</em> newspaper. John Ross served as principal chief of this tribe as it contested <em>Worcester v. Georgia</em>, and Sequoyah invented a syllabary alphabet for these people. The Treaty of New Echota led to their relocation from Georgia under the Indian Removal Act of 1830. For the point, name this tribe forcibly removed by Winfield Scott in the Trail of Tears.", "answer": "<b><u>Cherokee</u> </b> [Zihan Zhen<u>g]</u>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The first word in this title means \u201cocean,\u201d signifying great knowledge. The \u201cGreat Fifth\u201d of these figures constructed their Potala palace. Those who hold this office are considered a <em>yang</em> <em>srid,</em> or reincarnation, of its first holder, Dge-\u2019dun-grub-pa. The 14th and current holder of this office, Tenzin Gyatso, fled to India in 1959 after his homeland revolted against communist  China. For the point, name this leader of \u201cYellow Hat\u201d Tibetan Buddhists.", "answer": "the <b><u>Dalai Lama</u></b> [or <b><u>Rgyal-ba Rin-po-che</u></b>]  [Saul Hankin]", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Agabus the Decapolitan narrates a novel about this man by Robert Graves whose title  declares him a \u201cKing\u201d. This man is taught the ways of hedonism by a shepherd and learns of his prodigious fishing talent in a 1991 novel. He hallucinates a long dream sequence in which he has a large family in a novel adapted into a 1988 Martin Scorsese film. Jose Saramago and Nikos Kazantzakis, respectively, wrote about <em>The Gospel According to</em> and <em>The Last Temptation of</em> this man. For the point, name this religious leader from Nazareth.", "answer": "<b><u>Jesus</u><u>Christ</u></b> [accept either underlined answer; accept<em><b><u>King Jesus</u></b></em>] [Rob Carso<u>n]</u>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}], "bonuses": []}